Guide to the Haldane Macfall Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Haldane Macfall collection
1894-1944
GEN MSS 1079
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.26
(14 boxes)
The collection includes manuscripts, typescripts, and proofs of books, essays, and plays including a biography of Aubrey Beardsley, and the novels The Splendid Wayfaring and The Three Students; originals and proofs of illustrations, bookplates, and cover art; correspondence; and contracts with publishers. The majority of the correspondence consists of Macfall's outgoing letters to Earl E. Fisk, a British-born book collector, anthologist and insurance agent who lived in Green Bay, Wisconsin, and assisted Macfall in placing his books with American publishers.
Macfall, Haldane, 1860-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was purchased on the Francis O. Matthiessen Fund, 1956. Other items were the gifts of Mrs. Leon Godchaux, 1948, and E. L. Sampter, 1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Earl Fisk Papers (GEN MSS 342). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Haldane Macfall (1860-1928)
Chambers Haldane Cooke Macfall was a British military officer who authored works on art history and criticism, several novels, and numerous essays. He designed and illustrated many of his own works as well as bookplates and cover art, and exhibited works at the Royal Academy. He was married to Mabel Plumridge Macfall. He died in 1928.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes manuscripts, typescripts and proofs of books, essays, and plays including Aubrey Beardsley, The Splendid Wayfaring, and The Three Students; original and proofs of illustrations, bookplates, and cover art; correspondence; and contracts with publishers. The majority of the correspondence consists of Macfall's outgoing letters to Earl E. Fisk, a British-born book collector, anthologist and insurance agent who lived in Green Bay, Wisconsin, and assisted Macfall in placing his books with American publishers.
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Illustration of books -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- England; Bookplates -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- 20th Century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- England -- 20th Century; Fisk, Earl E.; Macfall, Haldane, 1860-1928; Macfall, Mabel Plumridge
- Books
  - Aubrey Beardsley, [1927?]-1928, undated; 10 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Two corrected typescripts, one with proofs of the illustrations inserted; carbon typescript of a critique of the book with autograph manuscript notations; and press clippings relating to the publication.
  - Beautiful Children, [1909?] (Box 1)
    Page proofs, corrected.
  - The Book of Lovat Claud Fraser, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    Two autograph manuscript drafts, one with proofs of illustrations inserted.
  - The French Pastellists, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    Autograph manuscript of the foreword accompanied by corrected page proofs of the book.
  - Ibsen: The Man, His Art, and His Significance, 1906 (Box 2)
    Typescript, carbon, with manuscript corrections.
  - The Modern Genius, [1911]; 4 (Box 3)
    Autograph manuscript of the title page and foreword, accompanied by page proofs of the book, volume 8 in his multi-volume work, A History of Painting.
  - "The Patchouli Decadents", undated (Box 3)
    Autograph manuscript.
  - "Sin", undated (Box 4)
    Typescript carbon with manuscript corrections.
  - Songs of the Immortals [volume of poems edited by Haldane Macfall], [1925-1926]; 4 (Box 4)
    Paste-up dummy, corrected, and illustrations.
  - The Splendid Wayfaring, circa 1913-1920, undated; 8 (Box 5)
    Autograph manuscript "scheme" of the book prepared for Earl E. Fisk; carbon typescript preface, with manuscript corrections; typescript, carbon preface by Frank Brangwyn with manuscript copy in the hand of Earl E. Fisk; "A Personal Note on Haldane MacFall," by Edward Gordon Craig, typescript, corrected, accompanied by two carbon typescripts and galley proofs; typescript of the book with manuscripts corrections; paste-up dummy of proofs with illustrations; typescript, carbon, with manuscript corrections of the preface; and a copy of the book interleaved with clippings and correspondence.
  - The Three Students, 1925-1926; 3 (Box 6)
    Typescript, carbon, with manuscript corrections, bound with a photograph of his drawing for the endpaper for the first American edition (1926); and two typescripts with manuscript corrections.
  - The Three Students (continued), 3 (Box 7)
    Typescripts and proofs of a preface, corrected, by Earl E. Fisk; two trial book covers; and a scrapbook of clippings, reviews and correspondence concerning the book.
  - "The World Chaos", 1926-1928, undated (Box 7)
    Typescript with manuscript corrections; accompanied by press clippings on Mussolini and the Scopes trial.
- Essays
  - "Art and Life," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Babette," typescript, corrected (Box 7)
  - "The Blood Toll," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 7)
  - "Christ's Mass or Neitzsche's?," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Deaf Prophet of Prussia," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Matinee Girl," typescript corrected, [1906?] (Box 8)
  - "Molly," typescript with manuscript corrections, undated (Box 8)
  - "Pictures for Pence," typescript, with manuscript corrections, 1912 (Box 8)
  - "Purification of the Unlicked Cub," two typescripts, corrected, with two fragmentary typescripts, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Sentimental Ostler," typescript with manuscript corrections, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Theatre and the Puritan," autograph manuscript address to the Players Club with bound manuscript, "The Puritan and the Theatre", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Third Man," by "Hal Dane," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Typewriter Girl," typescript corrected, undated (Box 8)
  - "Notes for an Address Upon the Ultimate Significance of Art," autograph manuscipt, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous essay and prose writings, autograph manuscripts, 1912-1928 (Box 8)
- Volumes containing clippings of essays by Haldane Macfall
  - "Essays by H. M.", 1913-1927 (Box 8)
  - "Various Essays", 1909-1923 (Box 8)
  - "Various Essays of the Imagination", 1906-1912 (Box 9)
- Playscripts
  - "The Discriminators," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9)
  - "The Fear of Robert Clive," two typescripts, corrected, 1896 (Box 9)
  - "The Three Students," typescript, corrected; with bound typescript carbon, corrected with typescript and manuscript notes laid in, 1907; 2 (Box 9)
- Manuscript and typescript notes and writings by Haldane Macfall and Earl E. Fisk concerning a Macfall bibliography, 1926 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook volumes
  Volumes containing press clippings, notes, and other ephemera relating to Macfall's writings.
  - "Beware the German's Peace!", 1911-1918 (Box 10)
  - "Concerning The Masterfolk ", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Wooings of Jezebel Pettyfer", 1913-1944 (Box 10)
- Art Work
  - Pursuasions to Joy by Earl E. Fisk, [1925-1926?] (Box 11)
    Paste-up dummy of proofs with drawings by Haldane Macfall.
  - Proofs of designs and cover title pages of books published by J.C. & E.C. Jack, undated (Box 11)
  - Trial bindings and cover designs for The Wooing of Jezebel Pettyfer and Poet's Country, undated (Box 11)
  - Cover design for The Wooing of Jezebel Pettyfer, undated (Box 11)
  - Bookplate designs, 1925, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    Includes bookplate designs for Haldane Macfall, Earl A. Fisk, Alfred A. Knopf, and George R. B. Bellew.
  - "Bargaining for Dinner in West Africa," pen and ink and water color drawing, undated (Box 11)
  - "Enter the Queen," proof of illustration for The Three Students, undated (Box 14)
  - "My Negro Magician," pen and ink drawing, 1894 (Box 11)
  - Two small pen and ink drawings, 1926 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous art work, undated (Box 11)
- Clippings, publicity material, etc., 1911-1927 (Box 11)
- Photographs of Haldane Macfall, undated (Box 11)
- Outgoing correspondence
  Includes letters by Macfall to Earl E. Fisk, publishers, and admirers.
  - Björkman, Edwin, 1926 August 12 (Box 12)
  - Fisk, Earl E., 1923 Jun 17, 1924 November 1 (Box 12)
  - Fisk, Earl E., 1923-1927; 8 (Box 12)
  - Fisk, Earl E., 1928-1930; 3 (Box 13)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1926 November 29 (Box 13)
  - Richards, Grant, 1903-1904 (Box 13)
  - Wilson, Mr., 1927 May 8 (Box 13)
    Removed from Macfall and Dion Clayton Cathrop's Rouge (London: Brown, Langham, and Co. Ltd.) 1906.
  - Incoming correspondence, 1909-1928 (Box 13)
    Includes letters to Macfall by publishers and admirers.
- Contracts with publishers, 1904-1929 (Box 13)
  Includes contracts with Harper, Simon & Schuster, and Knopf.
- Copies of collection catalog cards (Box 13)